Reimagine what data can help you do.
データで何ができるのか もう一度考えてみましょう
I'm going to be using Google Maps to illustrate several key points.
Googleマップを使って要点をお話しします
Take this map for example.
この地図を見てください
Every morning I glance at my phone, and it tells me the way to get to work.
私は毎朝 スマートフォンを見て 通勤経路を確認します
There are three possible routes.
通勤ルートは3つあります
And today, the highlighted route is the fastest.
今日はハイライトされた ルートが速いようですね
Sometimes I do go to Google Seattle,
シアトルのGoogleに行くときには
crossing the floating bridge across Lake Washington.
ワシントン湖の浮き橋を渡ります
And Maps tells me, helpfully, that the bridge is closed today.
マップによると今日は橋が通行止めです
You could think of this as being just a set of rules.
ただのルールセットだと考えられるでしょう
Sure, Google has to collect a lot of data to make this use case possible.
もちろんGoogleはこのユースケースのために 多くのデータを集めました
Where the roads are for one, the traffic on each road, bridge closures.
道路の位置や渋滞情報 橋の通行止めなどです
But the algorithm itself, routing algorithms between point A and
しかしアルゴリズム自体は 制限付きのA地点からB地点までの
point B subject to a set of constraints, that is just the A* algorithm.
ルーティングアルゴリズムで これは単にA*アルゴリズムです
The A* algorithm is started undergraduate computer science classes.
大学のコンピュータサイエンスの授業で 習うレベルのものです
So it's not that complex once you have the data.
ですからデータさえあれば 複雑ではありません
This is the kind of thing you can do for whole countries at a time.
国全体のデータも一度に処理できます
Get data on the road network, provide routing directions.
道路網のデータを入手し ルート情報を出力します
Traffic and bridge closures are a little more difficult in that you have to work
渋滞情報や橋の通行止めなどは少し厄介で
with a bunch of smaller government entities.
地方自治体からの情報が必要です
But it's still not such a huge data problem.
それでも大したデータ問題ではありません
The logic, once you have the data, seems to be quite tractable.
理論としては データさえあれば簡単です
But now take the case in the middle, still Maps.
では中央のケースはどうでしょうか 引き続きマップを使用します
I was in Japan, making my way from my hotel to the Google office.
日本でホテルから Google社に向かっていました
I'm in a subway station called Roppongi, and
六本木という地下鉄の駅でしたが
Maps tells me that I'm on floor number two of the subway station.
マップによると地下鉄の2階にいたようです
How does it know?
なぜわかったのでしょう？
Whatever the data sources it uses, wi-fi points, barometric pressure,
Wi-Fi地点や気圧 歩く速度など データが何であれ
typical walking speed, it's pretty obvious that this cannot be a simple set of rules.
ルールセットだけでは わからないことは確かです
Plus the relevant data to train the model and
さらにモデルをトレーニングする 適切なデータや
the relevant data to keep the model remaining fresh.
モデルを最新情報で 更新し続けることが必要です
Once you have the data,
データが揃ったところで
you're now going to use machine learning to sidestep having to write the logic.
機械学習を使い 理論を書かずに済むようにします
Maps here is anticipating that you might want to know if you
マップはここであなたが 建物の何階にいるかを
are in a multi-story building.
知りたいだろうと予想します
What else can Maps anticipate?
マップは他にどんなことを予想しますか？
Take the map on the right, still in Japan.
右の地図をご覧ください まだ日本にいます
I glance at my phone, in between meetings, and
会議の合間にスマートフォンを見ると
notice that I was getting a recommendation.
おすすめ情報が出ています
Maps is now connecting a past history, that I like art, that I like museums, and
マップが履歴から 私がアートや美術館が好きなことや
that I am in Japan, to now recommend things to me.
現在日本にいることを予想し おすすめ情報を出したのです
This is even more of a data problem.
これなどデータ問題そのものです
The machine learning is what allows the original limited how to get from point
機械学習はA地点からB地点への ルート検索から始めて
A to point B, how to take that to now become a virtual assistant.
バーチャルアシスタントにまでなりました
Personalization of the Maps service is possible only with machine learning.
マップのパーソナライズは 機械学習でのみ可能です
So machine learning is about scaling beyond handwritten rules.
機械学習とは手書きのルールを越えて 拡張することです
But then you start being able to do things that you could never achieve
手書きのルールでは不可能だったことが
if you were writing handwritten rules.
今や可能なのです
So think back to your business.
あなたのビジネスを考えましょう
Your business analysts are essentially looking at the bulk of your business.
ビジネスアナリストは事業の全体像を見ます
That's akin to the use case on the left,
左のユースケースがその一例です
the stuff that everybody in the county needs.
この国の誰もが必要とするもの
One set of rules for everyone.
統一されたルールセットです
You might be thinking of machine learning as a way to do the things in the middle.
機械学習とは真ん中のようなタスクだと 思うかもしれません
Of being able to take the data that you happen to have, and
入手したデータを
training a machine learning model.
機械学習モデルのトレーニングに使うのです
But think of machine learning as a way to get to the kinds of things on the right.
しかし機械学習を右のようなタスクに 使うことを考えてみてください
Of being able to personalize your services for each one of your customers.
顧客ごとにサービスをパーソナライズします
And notice a question at the bottom of the card on the right,
右のカードの下部にある質問を見ると
asking the user, is this card useful right now?
このカードはお役に立っていますか？ とあります
Asking for user feedback to keep improving the model.
モデル改善のためにユーザーの フィードバックを求めています
What's needed though, in this transformation from the left,
しかし一般的な左の例から
which is quite generic, to the right, which is quite personalized?
パーソナライズされた右の例に移行するには どうすればいいでしょう？
What's needed?
何が必要ですか？
Data and lots of it.
大量のデータです
The rules and models are actually quite simple.
ルールとモデルは非常に単純です
So if machine learning is a rocket engine, data is the fuel.
機械学習がロケットのエンジンなら データは燃料です
As we get into complex models and various ways of tuning a model to get better and
複雑なモデルを構築し 改善のための調整を行っていると
better performance, it can be very easy to lose sight of a key point.
重要な点を見落としがちです
Data wins every time.
それは データが成功の鍵だということです
So given the choice between more data and more complex models,
ですから 大量のデータと複雑なモデルの どちらかを選ぶなら
spend your energy collecting more data.
データを集めることに専念してください
And by that I mean collecting not just more quantity, also more variety.
量だけではなく多様性も重要です
For example, imagine that your data consists of these fractals.
データがこうしたフラクタル形状だとします
If you're zoomed way in you won’t see the patterns, you don’t have enough data.
集中しすぎるとパターンが見えません データが不足しているからです
So you'd end up sticking to very complex rules.
だから非常に複雑なルールに 従わねばなりません
But as you get more and more data, hopefully you fill out the domain and
しかし データが増えるにつれ視野が広がり
the overall pattern starts to become more evident.
全体のパターンが明らかになっていきます
So ML strategy is first and foremost a data strategy.
ML戦略で最も重要なのは データ戦略なのです